International Ladies Garment Workers Union. Schlesinger, Benjamin, President. Records, 1928-1932. 5780/010
Kheel Center for Labor-Management Documentation & Archives
International Ladies Garment Workers Union. Benjamin Schlesinger, President. Records
1928-1932.
Kheel Center for Labor-Management Documentation & Archives
International Ladies' Garment Workers' Union. President's Office.
5780/010
2 cubic feet
2 linear ft.
Correspondence, subject files.
Correspondence and subject files relating to Schlesinger's term, October 1928 to June 1932.
3436401
General
Contact Information:
Kheel Center for Labor-Management Documentation and Archives Martin P. Catherwood Library 227 Ives Hall Cornell University Ithaca, NY 14853 (607) 255-3183 kheel_center@cornell.edu http://www.ilr.cornell.edu/library/kheel
Compiled by:
Robert A. Lazar
Date completed:
June, 1977
EAD encoding:
Casey S. Westerman, July 16, 2002
Biographical / Historical
Files of the International Ladies' Garment Workers' Union (ILGWU) president Benjamin Schlesinger during his final term as president, from October 1928 to June 1932.
Schlesinger was a Jewish immigrant from Lithuania who began working in the garment industry in Chicago as a teenager. He became a union organizer soon after and rose quickly in the ranks of the Chicago Cloakmakers' Union. He served as president of the ILGWU for a brief time in 1903, and again from 1914 to 1923. Later, he was business manager of the Jewish Daily Forward in Chicago. He died in office on June 6, 1932.
Scope and Contents
Topics covered in these materials include: communist activity in the garment industry unions; contract negotiations; Schlesinger's role as business manager of the Jewish Daily Forward (Chicago); labor disputes in the women's garment industry of New York City; racketeering; socialism; garment industry strikes in New York City (including the 1929 Cloakmakers' Strike and the 1930 Dressmakers' Strike); the Tom Mooney Defense Committee; relations between manufacturers' associations and the union; union conventions; union elections; union finances; and worker education.
Individuals and organizations represented in the collection include: the Amalgamated Bank of New York; the Affiliated Dress Manufacturers' Association; the AFL (including letters from William Green); the Associated Raincoat Manufacturers of New York; Brookwood Labor College; Abraham Cahan; Thomas C.T. Crain; Eugene Debs; David Dubinsky; ILGWU Locals 8, 10 and 50; Sidney Hillman; Morris Hillquit; Charles Kreindler; Salvatore Ninfo; the Rand School of Social Science; Franklin D. Roosevelt; Arnold Rothstein; Jacob H. Schiff; Mortimer L. Schiff; Norman Thomas; Samuel Untermyer; B.C. Vladeck; and the Wholesale Dress Manufacturers' Association.
Related Materials
5780/009. Benjamin Schlesinger. President's records, 1914-1923.
Arrangement
Correspondence and subject files are arranged alphabetically within each section.
Arrangement
Series I. General correspondence.
Box 1
Series II. Subject files.
Boxes 1-4
Series III. Miscellaneous items.
Box 4
Conditions Governing Access
Access to the collections in the Kheel Center is restricted. Please contact a reference archivist for access to these materials.
Forverts (Chicago, Ill.); Clothing workers -- Labor unions -- United States; Clothing workers -- Labor unions -- New York (State) -- New York; Labor unions -- Clothing workers; Women's clothing industry -- United States; Women's clothing industry -- New York -- New York; Clothing trade -- United States; Clothing trade -- New York -- New York; Clothing workers -- United States; Clothing workers -- New York -- New York; Strikes and lockouts -- Clothing trade -- New York -- New York; Strikes and lockouts -- Clothing trade -- United States; Industrial relations -- United States; Industrial relations -- New York -- New York; Working class -- Education -- New York -- New York; Labor unions and communism -- United States; Socialism -- United States; Correspondence; Organization files; International Ladies' Garment Workers' Union; Cahan, Abraham, 1860-1951.; Crain, Thomas C. T. (Thomas Crowell Taylor), 1860-1942.; Debs, Eugene V. (Eugene Victor), 1855-1926.; Dubinsky, David, 1892-; Green, William, 1872-1952.; Hillman, Sidney, 1887-1946.; Hillquit, Morris, 1869-1933.; Ninfo, Salvatore.; Roosevelt, Franklin D. (Franklin Delano), 1882-1945.; Rothstein, Arnold, 1882-1928.; Schiff, Jacob H. (Jacob Henry), 1847-1920.; Schiff, Mortimer L.; Schlesinger, Benjamin, 1876-1932.; Thomas, Norman, 1884-1968.; Untermyer, Samuel, 1858-1940.; Vladeck, B. (Baruch Charney), 1886-1935.; Affiliated Dress Manufacturers' Association.; Amalgamated Bank of New York.; Amalgamated Ladies' Garment Cutters' Union.; American Federation of Labor.; Associated Raincoat Manufacturers of New York.; Brookwood Labor College (Katonah, N.Y.); International Clothing Workers' Federation.; International Ladies' Garment Workers' Union--Elections.; International Ladies' Garment Workers' Union--Finance.; International Ladies' Garment Workers' Union--Convention.; International Ladies' Garment Workers' Union--Presidents.; International Ladies' Garment Workers' Union. Local 8 (San Francisco, Calif.); International Ladies' Garment Workers' Union. Local 50 (New York, N.Y.); Mooney Molders Defense Committee.; Rand School of Social Science.; Waterproof Garment Manufacturers' Association.; Wholesale Dress Manufacturers' Association.
3436401
- I. General correspondence.
  - A. 1928-31., Includes correspondence between Associated Raincoat Manfacturers of N.Y. and Local 20 (Waterproof Garment Workers Union) on negotiations for agreement, 1928-30. (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - B., General Correspondence (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - C., Includes letters from Thomas C.T. Crain (N.Y. District Attorney) on racketeering, 1930 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - D., General Correspondence (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - E-F., General Correspondence (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - G., General Correspondence (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - H-L:., Includes list of bonds purchased by affiliated locals, 1929. (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - M., Includes ltr. from William Mack offering impartial assistance, 1929; Tom Mooney Defense Committee, 1929. (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - N., Includes letters to N.Y. Times and N.Y. World on Communist appeal in Daily Worker for Communists to participate in mass picketing in the dress industry, Feb. 1929. (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - O-P. (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - R., Includes Rand School letters, 1929-30. (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - S. (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - T., Ltrs. from Norman Thomas (4). (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - U-V., Includes letters to B. C. Vladeck (Manager), Jewish Daily Forward, 1929-30. (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - W-Z. (Box 1, Folder 15)
- II. Subject files.
  - Amalgamated Bank of N.Y.; 1924-31., Correspondence, financial matters; agreement between Union and bank; shares of Int'l. Union Bank as collateral for Union loan. (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Amalgamated Ladies Garment Cutters Union, Local 10., Ltr. urging Schlesinger to assume presidency, upon Morris Sigman's resignation, Nov. 14, 1928; Maurice Jacobs (Chairman), David Dubinsky (Manager), Local 10. (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - American Federation of Labor: Oct. 1928-July 1929., Includes letters from William Green. (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - AFL: Aug. 1929-32. (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - Associations.
    - Affiliated Dress Manfacturers Association, Inc., Correspondence re negotiations for agreements, 1929-32. (Box 1, Folder 20)
    - American Cloak and Suit Manfacturers Association, Inc., Benjamin Schlesinger conference address, March 1932. (Box 1, Folder 21)
    - Couturiers Association of N.Y., 1930 (Box 1, Folder 22)
    - Wholesale Dress Manfacturers Association 1929-32. (Box 1, Folder 23)
  - Brandeis, Louis., Birthday greetings to Schlesinger 1926, 1931. (Box 1, Folder 24)
  - Brookwood Labor College: 1928-32., Ltrs. from A.J. Muste (Chairman of Faculty); releases, statements issued by College re controversy with AFL over teaching policies, 1928; correspondence with Roger Baldwin and A.J. Muste on American Fund for Public Service loan to Union during N.Y.: Cloakmakers strike of 1926, 1929-32. (Box 1, Folder 25)
  - Cahan, Abraham: 1928-31., Correspondence (non-Union matters). (Box 1, Folder 26)
  - Chicago Joint Board: 1928-30., Includes correspondence with Morris Bialis (Manager). (Box 1, Folder 27)
  - Congratulatory Messages. Birthday, 1929. (Box 1, Folder 28)
  - Congratulatory Messages., Election to Union presidency, Oct. 1929 (Box 1, Folder 29)
  - Convention (20th), Union: 1929.
    - Convention call; memoranda to affiliates; telegrams to Raymond Ingersoll, James J. Walker, and Franklin D. Roosevelt (and his responses) on their help in terminating N.Y. Cloakmakers' strike of 1929. (Box 2, Folder 1)
    - Schlesinger's and Abraham Cahan's Convention addresses, Dec. (Box 2, Folder 2)
    - Ballots electing Convention delegates of Local 2 (Cloak and Suit Operators Union) and Local 9 (Cloak Finishers Union). (Box 2, Folder 3)
    - Committees., Includes lists of committee members; report of Committee on Law. (Box 2, Folder 4)
    - Committees, Citizens Committee to supervise elections for Convention delegates; Committee members (Jacob Billikopf, Arthur Garfield Hayes, Roger Baldwin) correspondence; report. (Box 2, Folder 5)
    - Committees., Credential Committee. Includes correspondence between Isidore Nagler (Chairman) and local affiliates on local indebtedness to Union; reports. (Box 2, Folder 6)
    - Invitations and responses; includes William Green, John L. Lewis, Morris Sigman, Norman Thomas, B.C. Vladeck. (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Convention (21st), Union: 1932.
    - General files. (Box 2, Folder 8)
    - General files. (Box 2, Folder 9)
    - Delegates and Alternates. Includes ballots electing delegates to Convention. (Box 2, Folder 10)
    - Invitations and responses, arranged alphabetically by correspondence (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - Dubinsky, David (and Hannah Haskel): 1928-30, 1932., Correspondence between Dubinsky and Benjamin Schlesinger, when Schlesinger is away from office. (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - Form Letters and Circulars: 1929-32. (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - General Executive Board., Ltr. from Special Committee informing Schlesinger of their decision to Separate Cloak and Dress Joint Board, April 1930; Dubinsky (Chairman), Salvatore Ninfo (Secretary). (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - Greetings (New Year's). (Box 2, Folder 15)
  - Hillquit, Morris: Nov. 1928-29., Correspondence on legal matters, negotiations for collective agreements. (Box 2, Folder 16)
  - Hillquit, Morris: 1930-32., Includes copies of letters on loan by Int'l. Madison Bank and Trust Co. to 130 E. 25th St. Corporation, 1930. (Box 2, Folder 17)
  - International Association of Machinists: 1930-31., Correspondence re Machinists' loan to Union. (Box 2, Folder 18)
  - International Unions: 1928., Union request for loan from various unions to help rehabilitate ILGWU. (Box 2, Folder 19)
  - Jewish Daily Forward, Chicago: 1923-28., Benjamin Schlesinger (Manager). Includes letters from Abraham Cahan and Eugene Debs (Box 2, Folder 20)
  - Kreindler, Charles: 1928-31. (Box 2, Folder 21)
  - Local 8: 1928., San Francisco, Calif. Correspondence with J. Mencoff. (Box 2, Folder 22)
  - N.Y. Cloakmakers Strike of 1929
    - July 2-15., Correspondence is arranged in chronological order; pre-strike items; includes ltr. to Cloak and Suit Manfacturers on negotiation for agreement; replies from individuals to whom copies of ltr. were forwarded; statement to Cloakmakers (Box 3, Folder 1)
    - May 28-July 4., Correspondence includes Shop Chairmen's meeting, May; General Executive Board manifesto to Cloakmakers, June? messages from local affiliates and individuals wishing Union success; letters pledging cooperation in aiding strikers; correspondence includes August Claessens with enclosed list of services for aiding strike; FDR ltr. inviting Union and manufacturers for conference in attempt to reach settlement, July 2. (Box 3, Folder 2)
    - July 15-July 16., Copy of ltr. to FDR from Industrial Council of Cloak Manfacturers stating their position, July 5; letters of support and congratulatory messages upon conclusion of strike; includes letters from Sidney Hillman, Norman Thomas. (Box 3, Folder 3)
    - July 7-24., Congratulatory messages and correspondence (Box 3, Folder 4)
    - July 25-Dec. 2., Includes congratulatory message from FDR, Aug. 1. (Box 3, Folder 5)
    - General items; includes list of General Strike Committee individuals; Union statements. (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - N.Y. Dressmakers Strike, 1930
    - Feb. 4-12., Jan. 31-Feb. 16, correspondence; FDR ltr. inviting Union to conference with manufacturers to settle strike, Feb. 4; Schlesinger statement at conference, Feb. 7? Herbert H. Lehman ltr. re Jobbers Association, Feb. 16. (Box 3, Folder 7)
    - Feb. 17-Mar. 16., Correspondence; congratulatory messages upon conclusion of strike. (Box 3, Folder 8)
    - Jan. 28., D.D. and Schlesinger addresses at Dressmakers mass meeting (Box 3, Folder 9)
  - Ninfo, Salvatore (Manager), Local 48 (Italian Cloak Makers Union): 1929-31. (Box 3, Folder 10)
  - Philadelphia: 1928, 1930., Includes correspondence on strike in Local 50. (Box 3, Folder 11)
  - Poland: 1920-31., Includes correspondence with Garment Workers Union; financial support to Jewish cultural institutions and newspapers. (Box 3, Folder 12)
  - Referendum for Electing General Officers: Jan. 7, 1930., Includes correspondence between Louis Reiff (Chairman), National Election Committee and local officers. (Box 3, Folder 13)
  - Referendum Election: 1930., Includes local letters informing Election Committee of election results. (Box 3, Folder 14)
  - Referendum Election: 1930., Same as above. (Box 3, Folder 15)
  - Rothstein, Arnold: Nov. 1928., D.D. telegrams to Schlesinger re District Attorney's evidence that Rothstein was connected with communist strikes in industry. (Box 3, Folder 16)
  - Schiff, Mortimer L. and Jacob H., Letter from Jacob on Union activities in relief for war sufferers in Europe (n.d. prior to 1920); letter from Mortimer on donation to Union. (Box 3, Folder 17)
  - Schlesinger, Speeches and Statements: 1928-Jan. 1929. (Box 3, Folder 18)
  - Schlesinger, Speeches and Statements: Feb. 1929-30. (Box 3, Folder 19)
  - Tailors and Garment Workers Union, London., Includes pub., Garment Workers, 1928; agreement between Wholesale Manfacturers Federation and Tailors Union, 1921. (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - Untermyer, Samuel: 1926, 1928. (Box 4, Folder 2)
- III. Miscellaneous items, 1897-30.
  - Newspaper Clipping Files. Articles by Schlesinger (n.d.) (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - Newspaper Clipping Files. Articles re Schlesinger or Union. (Box 4, Folder 4)
  - Notes (holograph)., 16 items (n.d.). (Box 4, Folder 5)
  - Photographs., 50 items. (Box 4, Folder 6)
  - Includes Socialist Party membership cards; membership dues card, Local 1; certificate of membership in Forward, 1916-25; military certifications, 1917-18 (3 items). (Box 4, Folder 7)
  - Includes Union constitution and by-laws, 1916; visas; autobiographical sketch, Dec. 1931. (Box 4, Folder 8)
  - Includes correspondence with family members in U.S.A. and Poland. (Box 4, Folder 9)
  - Originals. (Box 4, Folder 10a-10b)